<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-09T21:02:03+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Windleblo</title><subtitle>The cruising blog for S/V Windleblo, a Hallberg-Rassy 40. Follow our sailing adventures  from the Atlantic to the Pacific and beyond.
</subtitle><author><name>Jack</name></author><entry><title type="html">Cape Scott</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2024/06/23/cape-scott/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cape Scott" /><published>2024-06-23T22:03:45+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-23T22:03:45+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2024/06/23/cape-scott</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2024/06/23/cape-scott/"><![CDATA[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-21-1-1024x1024.jpg
Filename: PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-21-1-1024x1024.jpg
Date path: 2024/06/PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-21-1-1024x1024.jpg
Caption: Guise Bay
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Guise Bay]**
*Original filename: PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-21-1-1024x1024.jpg*

As I learned from the Healing Voyage two seasons ago, there are four “gauntlets” to endure when circumnavigating Vancouver Island: the Seymour Narrows, the Nahwitti Bar, Cape Scott, and the Brooks Peninsula. This time around, we decided to make the most of the third gauntlet, Cape Scott.

Conditions permitting, we would pull into Guise Bay, a small indent in the land just south of the Cape, anchor, and launch the dinghy to land ashore for a hike to the Cape Scott lighthouse.

Available information in pilot books and apps paints Guise Bay as a wild, somewhat precarious anchorage suitable for a stop only in settled weather. Inspecting the chart, rocky shoals protect the bay on the west, leaving it wide open to the Pacific to the south. One had to wonder how suitable it would be. Would ocean swell invade the bay, making it uncomfortable or even impossible to launch the dinghy? Would winds create chop causing more difficulty? We were determined to find out.

Leaving our previous anchorage, Bull Harbour, around Noon in light air, we crossed Nahwitti Bar without incident at high slack. The ebb tide pushed us along as we motored twenty nautical miles off the north end of Vancouver Island toward the Cape.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-23-1024x1024.jpg
Filename: PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-23-1024x1024.jpg
Date path: 2024/06/PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-23-1024x1024.jpg
Caption: Happy to be ashore
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Happy to be ashore]**
*Original filename: PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-23-1024x1024.jpg*

The chart shows the Cape Scott light right at the tip of the Cape. It says the light shines from a height of 70 meters. As soon as we got close enough, I started scanning the Cape through binoculars, but I saw no tall lighthouse. A more careful scan as we sailed closer revealed what appeared to be red rooves barely visible through the treetops on a rise just above the Cape. The light wasn’t on a tall tower, it was perched on a tall hill!

We motored on, rounding the Cape. Currents swirled and the ebb push abruptly ended. Very soon, we turned in on final approach into Guise Bay. A huge sea lion barked at us from his perch atop rocks guarding the entrance to the bay. His harem looked on approvingly.

Soon a pristine kilometer-long white sand beach came into view. The anchor set instantly in seven meters just off the beach. A black bear roamed the far end of beach, far enough away not to be a concern. It helped that we were downwind of him!

Even Neptune gazed favorably upon us. The swell was slight, less than one meter, and the winds were 10 knots from the north, coming over the land and not agitating the sea at all. Our plan could proceed. Once back from the hike, if conditions deteriorated we could still weigh anchor and make it the five nautical miles to the next anchorage south in daylight.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-22-3-1024x955.jpg
Filename: PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-22-3-1024x955.jpg
Date path: 2024/06/PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-22-3-1024x955.jpg
Caption: Windswept beach
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Windswept beach]**
*Original filename: PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-22-3-1024x955.jpg*

We launched the dinghy and rowed to shore, hauling the dinghy up to near the high tide line and lashing it to a stout log. Orange buoys marked the trailhead at the west end of the beach. Walking was easy through thick mossy forest on remnants of a plank and sand road built in the 1940’s to enable crews to shuttle between a top secret radar outpost on the hill and their barracks below.

Half an hour later we ascended the hill and emerged from the trees to encounter bright sunshine and manicured lawns on the lighthouse grounds. Several whitewashed buildings, all with red metal rooves, a helipad, and, of course, the lighthouse platform comprised the station. Presently, a lady in her 60’s came out of one of the buildings. She introduced herself as Jane and offered to tour us around.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-22-1-1024x1024.jpg
Filename: PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-22-1-1024x1024.jpg
Date path: 2024/06/PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-22-1-1024x1024.jpg
Caption: Atop the light
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Atop the light]**
*Original filename: PHOTO-2024-06-19-21-26-22-1-1024x1024.jpg*

The tour started with an ascent of a steep ladder to the top of the lighthouse platform where we were rewarded with stunning views of the Cape and adjacent seas on one side and the mountains of Vancouver Island on the other. The tour continued with a visit to the meteorological station, where we viewed old photos of the station under construction.

The radar station built during World War II was turned over to the Canadian Coast Guard in 1959 for conversion into a lighthouse. The seas around Cape Scott had long been known as a ship’s graveyard, making a light there essential. The light shines once every 10 seconds through an old-fashioned Fresnel lens, brightly visible to a range of 19 nautical miles out at sea. Three dwellings were built near the lighthouse to house the light keepers. In September 1981, a new tower was built to replace the old one on the radar foundation. Solar photovoltaic panels have now replaced two diesel generators for powering the station.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/20240620_115637-1024x1024.jpg
Filename: 20240620_115637-1024x1024.jpg
Date path: 2024/06/20240620_115637-1024x1024.jpg
Caption: Fresh catch
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Fresh catch]**
*Original filename: 20240620_115637-1024x1024.jpg*

The tour over, we bid Jane good day and retraced our steps over the rough plank trail back to Guise Bay, taking a brief detour for a stop at an alluring gravel beach with windswept evergreens atop rock spires. The weather forecast predicted steady conditions through the night with 10 knot winds over the land to the north and slight seas from the west. We elected to remain at anchor in Guise Bay, a real treat considering its remoteness. In the morning, the anchor up, we left the bay. Once clear of the bay, the winds increased to 15 knots. We pointed Windleblo south, switched off the motor, and put out a sliver of headsail and a trolling line to stern. Cape Scott still in view, two salmon struck my lure in turn, offering fresh catch for dinner.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">At It Again</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2024/06/16/at-it-again/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="At It Again" /><published>2024-06-16T01:45:32+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-16T01:45:32+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2024/06/16/at-it-again</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2024/06/16/at-it-again/"><![CDATA[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/20240612_131414-1024x1024.jpg
Filename: 20240612_131414-1024x1024.jpg
Date path: 2024/06/20240612_131414-1024x1024.jpg
Caption: 
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ]**
*Original filename: 20240612_131414-1024x1024.jpg*

We’re cruising north again aboard the _Windleblo_ , this time intending to circumnavigate Vancouver Island in six or seven weeks. We is me, Christine, and Frida, the 2024 crew. We drove _Windleblo_ out of her Canoe Cove berth June 3rd after a spring commissioning sequence that included standing rigging replacement and a new Starlink antenna clamped to the wind generator mast.

Six days and three stops later we were ready to transit the Seymour Narrows and begin our cruising in earnest. We’re now anchored on the north side of Broughton Island in a remote cove near the Broughton Lagoon, a brackish lake that requires navigation of tidal rapids to enter by dinghy.

All the good things about cruising are rushing back – fresh salty air, wind in the face, the feeling of freedom – and the metaphorical “daily rising tide” of a too long to do list has been replaced by the literal diurnal tidal cycle and the sounds of wind singing in the rigging and waves lapping at the hull.

Helping to keep spirits high is Frida. Sailing with a dog has its downsides (lots of dinghy trips to shore!). But whatever the inconveniences, they are more than compensated by the uninhibited curiosity, boundless energy, and warm loving gazes a dog brings to the mix. And Frida is proving to be a quick study in boat dog competencies, relearning quickly all the lessons from the Healing Voyage of two seasons ago – how to stay calm when heeling over in a stiff breeze, how to jump into the dinghy and back onto the boat, and of course how to hold her pee until its business time. One thing she has yet to figure out, though, is the purpose of the little green astroturf mat put out on the deck when we’re at anchor. She still thinks it’s for lounging, not peeing! Maybe soon we’ll have a breakthrough.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/20240610_173436-1024x1024.jpg
Filename: 20240610_173436-1024x1024.jpg
Date path: 2024/06/20240610_173436-1024x1024.jpg
Caption: She hasn’t figured it out
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: She hasn’t figured it out]**
*Original filename: 20240610_173436-1024x1024.jpg*]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Northernmost Reach</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/07/16/northernmost-reach/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Northernmost Reach" /><published>2023-07-16T00:50:46+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-16T00:50:46+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/07/16/northernmost-reach</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/07/16/northernmost-reach/"><![CDATA[A lot of water under the keel since R2AK.

Many, many highs. A few lows. Extraordinary overall.

Among the highs:

Putting _Windleblo_ through her paces with gale force following winds and three meter seas through Clarence Strait the day after leaving Ketchikan

Finally making it to Tebenkof Bay and paddleboarding through a remote cove there

## Catching crabs in Hoonah harbor

Watching National Geographic caliber sea life at South Marble Island, Glacier Bay

## Hiking above Mendenhall Glacier near Juneau

## Watching the Fourth of July parade in Juneau

## Witnessing a tidewater glacier calve in Glacier Bay

## Paddleboarding through icy growlers in Glacier Bay

Many whale sightings, including one so close we had to brake for it!

## Fresh salmon catch in the Lynn Canal

## Hiking to Burdette Cabin near Atlin

A couple of lows:

## Having the Webasto heater break down in Glacier Bay

Getting warm with electric heaters in Juneau only to fry the shore power fitting (argghh!)

We’re now in a place called Atlin in northern British Columbia, having sailed _Windleblo_ all the way up the Lynn Canal to the tourist town of Skagway, our northernmost port of call. (Four cruise ships stop in Skagway each day at this time of year.) We’ve left the boat in Skagway to take a week of shore leave in Atlin, sort of a vacation from our vacation. Of course, there are many stories to tell. But a picture is worth a thousand words, so I’ll let the ones below do all the talking

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230621_173215-scaled.jpg
Filename: 20230621_173215-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230621_173215-scaled.jpg
Caption: Entering hot springs with roaring creek adjacent
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Entering hot springs with roaring creek adjacent]**
*Original filename: 20230621_173215-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/IMG_1080-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_1080-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/IMG_1080-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Dungeness crab trapped in Hoonah harbor
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Dungeness crab trapped in Hoonah harbor]**
*Original filename: IMG_1080-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230704_112733-scaled.jpg
Filename: 20230704_112733-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230704_112733-scaled.jpg
Caption: Juneau Fourth of July parade
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Juneau Fourth of July parade]**
*Original filename: 20230704_112733-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230624_201442-scaled.jpg
Filename: 20230624_201442-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230624_201442-scaled.jpg
Caption: Crab feast!
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Crab feast!]**
*Original filename: 20230624_201442-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230704_112741-scaled.jpg
Filename: 20230704_112741-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230704_112741-scaled.jpg
Caption: Marching in the Juneau Fourth of July parade
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Marching in the Juneau Fourth of July parade]**
*Original filename: 20230704_112741-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230617_084842-2-scaled.jpg
Filename: 20230617_084842-2-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230617_084842-2-scaled.jpg
Caption: Whale crossing!
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Whale crossing!]**
*Original filename: 20230617_084842-2-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230702_163037-scaled.jpg
Filename: 20230702_163037-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230702_163037-scaled.jpg
Caption: View spot on the hike above the Mendenhall Glacier near Juneau
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: View spot on the hike above the Mendenhall Glacier near Juneau]**
*Original filename: 20230702_163037-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230705_121828-768x1024.jpg
Filename: 20230705_121828-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230705_121828-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Fresh catch of the day!
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Fresh catch of the day!]**
*Original filename: 20230705_121828-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230627_1816192-1024x671.jpg
Filename: 20230627_1816192-1024x671.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230627_1816192-1024x671.jpg
Caption: Whale dives near Russell Island, Glacier Bay
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Whale dives near Russell Island, Glacier Bay]**
*Original filename: 20230627_1816192-1024x671.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230627_131646-scaled.jpg
Filename: 20230627_131646-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230627_131646-scaled.jpg
Caption: Paddle boarding near Margerie Glacier, Glacier Bay
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Paddle boarding near Margerie Glacier, Glacier Bay]**
*Original filename: 20230627_131646-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230627_095815-1024x768.jpg
Filename: 20230627_095815-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230627_095815-1024x768.jpg
Caption: The sun finally comes out in Glacier Bay
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: The sun finally comes out in Glacier Bay]**
*Original filename: 20230627_095815-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230627_1724082.jpg
Filename: 20230627_1724082.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230627_1724082.jpg
Caption: Bald eagle perched on floating ice near Lamplugh Glacier, Glacier Bay
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Bald eagle perched on floating ice near Lamplugh Glacier, Glacier Bay]**
*Original filename: 20230627_1724082.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230628_1124582-1024x765.jpg
Filename: 20230628_1124582-1024x765.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230628_1124582-1024x765.jpg
Caption: Sea Lions on South Marble Island, Glacier Bay
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Sea Lions on South Marble Island, Glacier Bay]**
*Original filename: 20230628_1124582-1024x765.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/IMG_1095-1-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_1095-1-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/IMG_1095-1-scaled.jpg
Caption: The offending shore power fitting
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: The offending shore power fitting]**
*Original filename: IMG_1095-1-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230625_192542-768x1024.jpg
Filename: 20230625_192542-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230625_192542-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Another humpback nearby!
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Another humpback nearby!]**
*Original filename: 20230625_192542-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/20230621_081619.jpg
Filename: 20230621_081619.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/20230621_081619.jpg
Caption: Yet another humpback very close, Gut Bay, Baranof Island
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Yet another humpback very close, Gut Bay, Baranof Island]**
*Original filename: 20230621_081619.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/IMG_1134-3-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_1134-3-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/IMG_1134-3-1024x768.jpg
Caption: On the trail to Burdette Cabin
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: On the trail to Burdette Cabin]**
*Original filename: IMG_1134-3-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/IMG_1151-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_1151-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/IMG_1151-1024x768.jpg
Caption: View of Atlin Lake a peaks beyond on ridge southwest of Burdette Cabin
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: View of Atlin Lake a peaks beyond on ridge southwest of Burdette Cabin]**
*Original filename: IMG_1151-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/IMG_1163-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_1163-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/07/IMG_1163-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Burdette cabin near Atlin Lake, northern British Columbia
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Burdette cabin near Atlin Lake, northern British Columbia]**
*Original filename: IMG_1163-768x1024.jpg*]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A lot of water under the keel since R2AK.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Race to Alaska</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/06/20/race-to-alaska/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Race to Alaska" /><published>2023-06-20T02:18:43+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-20T02:18:43+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/06/20/race-to-alaska</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/06/20/race-to-alaska/"><![CDATA[From [R2AK.com](https://web.archive.org/web/20240620074654/http://www.r2ak.com/):

“The inside passage to Alaska has been paddled by native canoes since time immemorial, sailing craft for centuries, and after someone found gold in the Klondike the route was jammed with steamboats full of prospectors elbowing each other out of the way for the promise of fortune.

It’s in the spirit of tradition, exploration, and self-reliance that Race to Alaska was born. R2AK is the first of its kind and North America’s longest human and wind powered race, and currently the largest cash prize for a race of its kind.

It’s like the Iditarod, on a boat, with a chance of drowning, being run down by a freighter, or eaten by a grizzly bear. There are squalls, killer whales, tidal currents that run upwards of 20 miles an hour, and some of the most beautiful scenery on earth.

You, a boat, a starting gun. $10,000 if you finish first, a set of steak knives if you’re second. Cathartic elation if you can simply complete the course. R2AK is a self-supported race with no supply drops and no safety net. Any boat without an engine can enter.

## In 2022, 41 teams were accepted and 19 finished.”

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/R2AK_FullCourse_Map_new-427x1024.jpg
Filename: R2AK_FullCourse_Map_new-427x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/R2AK_FullCourse_Map_new-427x1024.jpg
Caption: 
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ]**
*Original filename: R2AK_FullCourse_Map_new-427x1024.jpg*

## ++++++++++++

The Race to Alaska is put on each year by the [Northwest Maritime Center](https://web.archive.org/web/20240620074654/http://www.nwmaritime.org/), a 501(c)(3) non-profit based in Port Townsend, Washington. The Center mission? To engage people in the waters of our world in a spirit of adventure and discovery.

In 2019, our own Nikki Henderson joined the all-female “First Federal’s Sail Like a Girl” R2AK team. Finishing fourth, the team’s result was largely due to their decision to reverse course to help another team in distress. (The move was without accommodation by race organizers.)

At it again in 2023, Nikki joined R2AK’s “We Brake for Whales” team in her second bid for victory.

Eight people, never having sailed together before, assembled in Port Townsend in early June to prepare for the race. The Stage One shake down from Port Townsend to Victoria gave them a chance to learn about each other and their ship, a heavy water-ballasted 40-foot Lyman Morse sloop made in Thomaston, Maine, aptly named Gray Wolf. The result set the tone. “We Brake for Whales” was first to enter Victoria harbor.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/IMG_0969-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_0969-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/IMG_0969-scaled.jpg
Caption: The winning boat approaches the dock in Ketchikan
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: The winning boat approaches the dock in Ketchikan]**
*Original filename: IMG_0969-scaled.jpg*

Now came the real Type 2 fun.

Stage Two is a 710-nautical-mile test of skill and stamina through some of the world’s trickiest waters. With no official course and only one required waypoint, racers choose their own way north. To start, most opt to go inside Vancouver Island to avoid foul winds and waves on the island’s west coast. This year was no exception.

The only hitch? Racers must cope with finicky tidal currents, including 15-knot rips through the Seymour Narrows about half way up the island. Entering at the wrong time, especially without a motor, invites disaster. This natural gate must be transited as close to slack as possible, forcing lead boats to wait as slower boats catch up.

Team We Brake for Whales was among the first through the narrows and beyond, carried by strong following currents into Johnstone Strait toward the top of the island. It was there that the die was cast for how the 2023 R2AK would play out.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/IMG_1030-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_1030-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/IMG_1030-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Team banner: We Brake for Whales
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Team banner: We Brake for Whales]**
*Original filename: IMG_1030-768x1024.jpg*

Northwest winds set in as the racers emerged from the protected waters behind Vancouver Island. Forecast to build over the next few days, it quickly became clear the conditions would work in Gray Wolf’s favor.

With a stout, stiff monohull, and large, strong crew, including five veteran offshore racers and four past R2AK finishers, Team We Brake for Whales steadily outpaced the competition. The contenders piloted multihulls, trimarans mostly, which proved incapable of pointing high enough to match Gray Wolf’s progress. What’s more, their less sturdy composition was soon revealed through broken halyards and delaminated hulls. One by one, the followers took refuge from the headwinds as Gray Wolf and her crew tacked faithfully upwind for three days, sometimes into near gale 30-knot winds, turning a 710-nautical-mile race into an 850-nautical-mile trial.

By the time Team We Brake for Whales crossed into the U.S., they had built a 60-nautical-mile lead. Fifty nautical miles later, they entered Thomas Basin in Ketchikan under wind and pedal-prop power, docked, and rang the victory bell at 5:59 a.m. on June 14th, more than one and a half days ahead of the second-place finisher.

On hand to greet the victors was a small cadre of race officials, media representatives, and crew friends and family, including Christine and me, the crew of S/V _Windleblo_ , who came equipped with a flugelhorn and whistle to blast as Gray Wolf approached the dock in the early morning chill.

Having sailed our own version of the race to Alaska, S/V Windleblo and crew covered a more meandering course from Vancouver through the Salish Sea, Queen Charlotte Sound, middle BC Coast, Fjordland Recreational Area, and Inside Passage to Prince Rupert, then across the Dixon Entrance and on to Ketchikan in a short 15 days. That put us in town in time to greet Nikki as she arrived victorious and be part of the evening dinner where she and her shipmates received the $10,000 first prize for the 2023 R2AK.

A retirement celebration for Christine, many whale, sea lion, seal, sea otter, grizzly bear, and bald eagle sightings, several hot spring soaks, the Prince Rupert Seafest, and following breezes were among the highlights of the _Windleblo’s_ voyage to Ketchikan. A few more images of the voyage and Nikki’s reception follow.

Read more about Nikki’s victory at [https://r2ak.com/2023-daily-updates/stage-2-day-8-team-we-brake-for-whales-a-boat-a-team-a-disease/](https://web.archive.org/web/20240620074654/https://r2ak.com/2023-daily-updates/stage-2-day-8-team-we-brake-for-whales-a-boat-a-team-a-disease/)

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/GFGW4945-768x1024.jpg
Filename: GFGW4945-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/GFGW4945-768x1024.jpg
Caption: The victor’s reception
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: The victor’s reception]**
*Original filename: GFGW4945-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/HSWK9409-1-1024x768.jpg
Filename: HSWK9409-1-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/HSWK9409-1-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Trumpeting a victorious arrival
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Trumpeting a victorious arrival]**
*Original filename: HSWK9409-1-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/IMG_0982-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_0982-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/IMG_0982-scaled.jpg
Caption: First step onto the dock for the victorious crew
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: First step onto the dock for the victorious crew]**
*Original filename: IMG_0982-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/IMG_0984-1-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_0984-1-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/IMG_0984-1-scaled.jpg
Caption: Ringing the victory bell
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Ringing the victory bell]**
*Original filename: IMG_0984-1-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/IMG_1009-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_1009-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/IMG_1009-1024x768.jpg
Caption: The pedal prop mounts on the transom
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: The pedal prop mounts on the transom]**
*Original filename: IMG_1009-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/IMG_1050-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_1050-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/IMG_1050-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Nikki with her $10,000 prize
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Nikki with her $10,000 prize]**
*Original filename: IMG_1050-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-02_1-768x1024.jpg
Filename: PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-02_1-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-02_1-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Southerly breezes propel S/V Windleblo northward in Queen Charlotte Sound
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Southerly breezes propel S/V Windleblo northward in Queen Charlotte Sound]**
*Original filename: PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-02_1-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-01_2-1024x768.jpg
Filename: PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-01_2-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-01_2-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Typical scenery, Kynoch Inlet, Fjordlland Recreational Area
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Typical scenery, Kynoch Inlet, Fjordlland Recreational Area]**
*Original filename: PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-01_2-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-02-768x1024.jpg
Filename: PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-02-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-02-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Southeast Alaska fashion in June
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Southeast Alaska fashion in June]**
*Original filename: PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-02-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-01-768x1024.jpg
Filename: PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-01-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2023/06/PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-01-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Waterfall plunging into the sea, Fjordland Recreational Area
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Waterfall plunging into the sea, Fjordland Recreational Area]**
*Original filename: PHOTO-2023-06-08-18-47-01-768x1024.jpg*]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From R2AK.com:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Begin Again</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/06/14/begin-again/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Begin Again" /><published>2023-06-14T16:44:34+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T16:44:34+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/06/14/begin-again</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/06/14/begin-again/"><![CDATA[## The storm passes

## Black clouds clear

## Damage done

## Pick up broken pieces

## Feel the sun

## Begin again

## Try to create

## Efforts fail

## Hard to accept

## Ashamed and embarrassed

## Not sure what’s next

## Begin again

## Socially outcast

## Feeling alone

## Emotions flood

## Look deep within

## Find the good

## Begin again

## Head spins

## Thoughts muddled

## Samsara unleashed

## Calm the mind

## Feel at peace

## Begin again

## A union dissolves

## Hearts break

## Life in tatters

## Find the meaning

## Seek what’s after

## Begin again]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The storm passes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Cruising Plan</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/05/03/2023-cruising-plan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Cruising Plan" /><published>2023-05-03T23:46:45+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-03T23:46:45+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/05/03/2023-cruising-plan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2023/05/03/2023-cruising-plan/"><![CDATA[## Spring Commissioning, Canoe Cove, BC; April 27 – May 21

May 21 – 25 San Juan Islands Shake Down; Deep Cove, BC (65 nm)

## Leg 1: BC Coast Cruise; May 26 – June 20 (500 nm)

## May 26 – 31 Deep Cove to Port McNeill

## Jun 1 – 4 Port McNeill to Bella Bella

## Jun 5 – 13 Fjordland

## Jun 14 – 17 Prince Rupert

Jun 18 – 19 Cross Dixon Entrance to Prince of Wales Island; clear U.S. Customs

## Leg 2: The Southeast; June 20 – Aug 8 (600 nm)

## Jun 20 – 27 Explore Prince of Wales Island

## Jun 28 – 30 Warm Springs

## Jul 1 – 4 Petersburg

## Jul 5 – 8 Sail to Juneau; explore Tracy Arm en route

Jul 9 – 18 Leave _Windleblo_ berthed in Juneau.

SHORE LEAVE. Travel to Atlin. Return ferry via Skagway.

## Jul 19 – 28 Explore Glacier Bay & Chicagof Island

## Jul 29 – 31 Sitka

Aug 1 – 7 Coastal cruising Baranof and Prince of Wales Islands

Aug 8 Cross Dixon Entrance to Prince Rupert; clear Canadian Customs

## Leg 3: Haida Gwaii; August 9 – September 8 (200 nm)

## Aug 9 – 10 Prince Rupert

## Aug 11 – 12 Cross to Sandspit

## Aug 13 Sandspit

## Aug 14 – 24 Explore Gwaii Haanas

Aug 25 – Sep 3 Leave Windleblo berthed in Skidegate.

SHORE LEAVE. Return to Vancouver.

## Sep 4 – 8 Explore Gwaii Haanas

Leg 5: Passage from Haida Gwaii to Vancouver Island; Sep 9 – 14 (400 nm)

Sep 9 – 11 Watch weather window for 250 nm crossing to Nootka Island

Sep 12 – 14 Continue passage transiting Straits of Juan de Fuca to Canoe Cove]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Commissioning, Canoe Cove, BC; April 27 – May 21]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Am Alive</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/08/07/i-am-alive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Am Alive" /><published>2022-08-07T04:13:42+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-07T04:13:42+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/08/07/i-am-alive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/08/07/i-am-alive/"><![CDATA[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/SVDZ6413-1024x629.jpg
Filename: SVDZ6413-1024x629.jpg
Date path: 2022/08/SVDZ6413-1024x629.jpg
Caption: 
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ]**
*Original filename: SVDZ6413-1024x629.jpg*

On the way to the Victoria airport, Uncle Bill met a woman at the Stone House, an excellent restaurant adjacent to Canoe Cove marina. They struck up a conversation and shared dinner. Before the meal ended, she gave him her card with her number on it.

Also written on the card was this tag line: “Life is precious, make the most of it!”

Unknown to Bill, this wasn’t just any woman. This was Jeanne Socrates, arguably the most famous blue water sailor alive today.

As hours turned into days and days into weeks following Jocelyn’s death, the question was posed to me, “What are you going to do now?”

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/IMG_0789-1-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_0789-1-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2022/08/IMG_0789-1-1024x768.jpg
Caption: 
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ]**
*Original filename: IMG_0789-1-1024x768.jpg*

It’s a reasonable question. After all, my life has been upended. All bets are off. The future is uncertain. Indeed, what should I do now?

One option I offered was “Maybe I’ll pull a Jeanne Socrates.”

Jeanne Socrates started sailing at age 48, first with her husband and then, following his death from cancer in 2003, on her own. She now holds the record for the oldest person to have circumnavigated the globe in a cruising sailboat solo, non-stop, and unassisted. Her route started and ended in Victoria and took her south of the five great southern capes. The voyage lasted 339 days fulfilling a dream she shared with her husband. When it ended in September, 2019, she was 77 years old. You can use this link to read more: [https://www.yachtingmonthly.com/cruising-life/jeanne-socrates-77-and-solo-non-stop-around-the-world-72022](https://web.archive.org/web/20230522032848/https://www.yachtingmonthly.com/cruising-life/jeanne-socrates-77-and-solo-non-stop-around-the-world-72022).

Circumnavigate the globe. That’d be one way to answer the question, “What are you going to do now?”

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image.png
Filename: image.png
Date path: 2022/08/image.png
Caption: Healing Voyage track
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Healing Voyage track]**
*Original filename: image.png*

Circumnavigate Vancouver Island. Another way to answer the question.

Today, I safely tucked the _Windleblo_ back into her slip at Canoe Cove, completing the circumnavigation.

## Now what?

Like most people, I keep “to do” lists. Call me corny, but a few years back I started putting as #1 on each daily list the assignment “Love wife.” Not because I needed reminding, but because each day it was my highest priority.

Once the fog of shock and disbelief at losing Jocelyn lifted, I was forced to consider a different start to my “to do” lists. Without much thinking, instead of “Love wife” I wrote “Love life.” Was it simply rhyme? Or a subliminal mandate? Perhaps living is my new highest priority. But how to live?

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/IMG_0360-2-1024x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0360-2-1024x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/08/IMG_0360-2-1024x1024.jpg
Caption: Welcoming committee representative
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Welcoming committee representative]**
*Original filename: IMG_0360-2-1024x1024.jpg*

The survivor often searches for reasons why. Why did she die? Why not me instead? These questions have run their course in my thinking and sometimes recur. My answers have run the gamut from, “It should have been me instead,” to “No, it shouldn’t have because I wouldn’t want her to suffer the pain I’m suffering now,” to “If it should have been me it would have been,” and others.

Reading Kessler, I’ve decided to turn the equation around by asking “Why did she live?” The answers to this question are far more satisfying. She lived so she could be my wife. She lived so she could bring two remarkable children into the world. She lived so she could learn and teach. She lived so she could help and love others. She lived so I could take care of her. She lived so she could enjoy living. Etc.

So what am I going to do now? I am going to keep on living. I am going to live in a way that honors Jocelyn as someone I love, someone who has influenced me deeply. In this, I will be part of her legacy.

And I’m going to find a way to obey Jeanne Socrates’ command: “Life is precious, make the most of it!”

I am alive.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/IMG_0042-1-917x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0042-1-917x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/08/IMG_0042-1-917x1024.jpg
Caption: Dear Jocelyn
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Dear Jocelyn]**
*Original filename: IMG_0042-1-917x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0178-1-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_0178-1-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0178-1-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Our wedding day
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Our wedding day]**
*Original filename: IMG_0178-1-1024x768.jpg*]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dear Follower</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/29/dear-follower/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dear Follower" /><published>2022-07-29T06:16:03+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-29T06:16:03+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/29/dear-follower</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/29/dear-follower/"><![CDATA[Thank you, dear follower, for sticking with me thus far, for caring enough to read these posts. I so appreciate knowing you are there, feeling your love, and receiving your reactions to my writing. It nourishes me as I carry on.

This morning I felt the grip of the anger monkey, the self-pity monster, and the other evil demons. I submitted to them for a while and found myself again despairing that Jocelyn is gone. I picked up the little book Roni gave me to help me through, “Healing After Loss,” and opened it. This passage appeared:

“We are called to be food and drink for one another.” – Wendy M. Wright

That’s how important to me you’ve become – as essential as food and water – by sharing the experience of the Healing Voyage with me through these posts.

But this street of sorrow runs two ways. If you’re following, you may be suffering too. Jocelyn touched many lives, was loved by many. My heart breaks for you, knowing you loved someone so dear to me, someone you too lost. This bond we now share compels me to want to help you with your trials as best I can just as you have helped me. Thank you for letting me be part of your life.

So, too, am I grateful for my brother, Bill, who has joined me throughout the Healing Voyage thus far. We have succeeded in reaching Ucluelet, a small fishing and tourism center on Vancouver Island’s west coast, where he will depart overland for Victoria and a return flight to his home in Rhode Island.

Celebratory beers in hand, Bill and I reminisced about highlights of the Healing Voyage, represented by these photos:

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0216-768x1024.jpeg
Filename: IMG_0216-768x1024.jpeg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0216-768x1024.jpeg
Caption: The Sunken Garden at Butchart Gardens, Victoria
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: The Sunken Garden at Butchart Gardens, Victoria]**
*Original filename: IMG_0216-768x1024.jpeg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0640-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_0640-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0640-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Voyage mascot through the galley hatch
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Voyage mascot through the galley hatch]**
*Original filename: IMG_0640-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0585-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0585-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0585-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Well reefed rounding the Brooks Peninsula
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Well reefed rounding the Brooks Peninsula]**
*Original filename: IMG_0585-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0635.jpg
Filename: IMG_0635.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0635.jpg
Caption: Bunsby Island jellyfish
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Bunsby Island jellyfish]**
*Original filename: IMG_0635.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0646-1024x613.jpg
Filename: IMG_0646-1024x613.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0646-1024x613.jpg
Caption: Frida treed a bear!
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Frida treed a bear!]**
*Original filename: IMG_0646-1024x613.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0677-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_0677-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0677-scaled.jpg
Caption: Rugged Point driftwood and beach
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Rugged Point driftwood and beach]**
*Original filename: IMG_0677-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0700-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0700-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0700-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Fresh catch
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Fresh catch]**
*Original filename: IMG_0700-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_1013-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_1013-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_1013-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Bacchante Bay view
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Bacchante Bay view]**
*Original filename: IMG_1013-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0987-595x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0987-595x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0987-595x1024.jpg
Caption: Hot Springs soak
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Hot Springs soak]**
*Original filename: IMG_0987-595x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0637-1024x473.jpg
Filename: IMG_0637-1024x473.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0637-1024x473.jpg
Caption: Alligator driftwood
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Alligator driftwood]**
*Original filename: IMG_0637-1024x473.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0882-1024x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0882-1024x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0882-1024x1024.jpg
Caption: Whale drone shot
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Whale drone shot]**
*Original filename: IMG_0882-1024x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0836-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0836-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0836-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Inside a First Nation church at Yuquot
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Inside a First Nation church at Yuquot]**
*Original filename: IMG_0836-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0486-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0486-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0486-768x1024.jpg
Caption: A proper British breakfast
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: A proper British breakfast]**
*Original filename: IMG_0486-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0826-576x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0826-576x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0826-576x1024.jpg
Caption: Doug and Donna, Keepers of the Nootka Lighthouse
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Doug and Donna, Keepers of the Nootka Lighthouse]**
*Original filename: IMG_0826-576x1024.jpg*

[https://youtube.com/shorts/iGWEdPfykaQ?feature=share](https://web.archive.org/web/20230522032848/https://youtube.com/shorts/iGWEdPfykaQ?feature=share)]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thank you, dear follower, for sticking with me thus far, for caring enough to read these posts. I so appreciate knowing you are there, feeling your love, and receiving your reactions to my writing. It nourishes me as I carry on.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Burl</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/26/the-burl/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Burl" /><published>2022-07-26T05:33:22+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-26T05:33:22+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/26/the-burl</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/26/the-burl/"><![CDATA[Who knew? Port McNeill, British Columbia, is home to the World’s Largest Burl.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0514-6-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_0514-6-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0514-6-scaled.jpg
Caption: 
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ]**
*Original filename: IMG_0514-6-scaled.jpg*

The “Ronning Burl” originated from a 525-year-old Sitka Spruce tree and weighs more than 20 tons.

Reading the information posted next to the burl, I learned that burls are both bad and good. They’re bad because they can weaken trees and make them susceptible to harmful diseases and wind damage. Burl wood has poor structural qualities for lumber. Also bad.

But burls are highly sought after by furniture woodworkers. Burl wood possesses tremendous natural beauty. Bark inclusions, pitch pockets, and diverse growth ring patterns create rich diversity in burl wood color, patterns, and irregularities, which is prized for decorative furniture such as coffee tables, wall clocks, and bowls. All good.

Like so many other things burls are either bad or good, depending on your perspective.

Reading Kessler, I learned that people who experience traumatic grief – grief triggered by a sudden loss – often have a hard time focusing on anything other than the trauma, the bad stuff. He tells of one case where a woman whose son had died unexpectedly could not get the image of her son in the morgue out of her mind. Kessler coached her to try to introduce a happy memory of her son – something good – whenever the horrible image came up. With practice, the happy memory takes hold and the hurtful image recedes. Over time, the good wins out over the bad.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0516-5-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0516-5-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0516-5-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Close up of the World’s Largest Burl
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Close up of the World’s Largest Burl]**
*Original filename: IMG_0516-5-768x1024.jpg*

Similarly, ever since I held Jocelyn as life left her, I have been haunted by the images burned into my brain during those final moments. They invade both my waking and sleeping hours, coming unbidden at seemingly random intervals.

My therapist explained to me that the brain is like a big filing cabinet. Each of your thoughts, images, and experiences gets put in an assigned file. But your brain has no file for a sudden traumatic experience. It goes haywire trying to figure out what to do with it.

Remembering the Kessler passage, I tried to think of a happy memory to supplant the traumatic images. What instantly popped into my mind might seem innocuous but held special meaning for me.

The day before she died, we had cast off from our slip at Canoe Cove and sailed ten nautical miles to Stuart Island, the northwestern-most island in the San Juan group. Our plan was to stay one night at the island, then cross to Port Townsend the next day.

Arriving at the island’s harbor, we found we were all alone. Normally a popular spot, there were no other boaters. It was April, just a bit early in the season for most folks.

We dinghied to shore and took a leisurely hike on empty trails through lush, moss-strewn woods to an old one-room schoolhouse that served the handful of families who lived on the island over the past century. A small unattended library was open next to the schoolhouse where we browsed the posters and photos about those people. Jocelyn seemed happy.

Walking back from the schoolhouse, we occasioned past a tree that had an interesting feature – a burl. We paused to inspect it.

Returning to the _Windleblo_ , we made dinner and read some before retiring.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_9978-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9978-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_9978-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Burled tree on Stuart Island
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Burled tree on Stuart Island]**
*Original filename: IMG_9978-768x1024.jpg*

Perhaps this memory jumped to the front of the line when I reflected on Kessler’s advice only because it was the most recent. But I think there was more to it. It stood out because to me it represents the best of our life together. Enjoyment of nature. Quality time together. Plus, I got to have Jocelyn all to myself. None of the distractions or demands of life at home. Just the two of us away from it all.

Of course, when I look back there are many memories to cherish.

Someone once told me that people will not remember the words you say to them; rather, they will remember the way you made them feel. Each of my memories of Jocelyn is colored by this notion.

Regardless of occasion or event, she had a manner that put you at ease. She listened. She empathized. With her, you couldn’t help but feel that she cared about you, that you were special to her. And her deeds proved the feeling was justified. She always put down whatever she was doing to help anyone who needed her.

Maybe I had a soft spot for her. Well, okay, I absolutely had a soft spot for her. I loved her more than anything.

But it wasn’t just me. You heard it over and over at her Ceremony of Gratitude. She had that effect on everyone.

Though I can catalogue the special occasions – the birthdays, holidays, vacations, trips, and so forth – for me the most special memories are the more routine. Little snippets of our life together that come to mind when I think of her.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG-0041-1024x712.png
Filename: IMG-0041-1024x712.png
Date path: 2022/07/IMG-0041-1024x712.png
Caption: I turned a close up of the Stuart Island burl into my screensaver.
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: I turned a close up of the Stuart Island burl into my screensaver.]**
*Original filename: IMG-0041-1024x712.png*

Sharing morning coffee as she solved a crossword puzzle. The kiss goodbye as I left for the office for the day. Sharing an evening meal after a long day at work. The click of her keypad as she entered numbers when she worked. The click of her knitting needles as we watched TV together on the loveseat recliner after dinner, sometimes playing footsie. Yardwork and gardening together on the weekends. Admiring baby clothes and blankets she had sewn to have ready as gifts just in case. And more.

Ironically, I cherish the time we spent together in isolation during that first long COVID winter. I would jokingly refer to it as our period of 254 consecutive “date nights.” Like on the _Windleblo_ , I didn’t have to share her with anyone.

Listed just before the item on developing a new self-identity in my grief therapist’s “Reconciliation Tasks” handout is Item #3: “Remember the person who’s gone.” Through memories, I can keep Jocelyn in my heart. The grief can morph into love.

Like a burl, what you see depends on your perspective. Trying to keep happy memories – the good stuff – front of mind can ward off pain and keep the bad stuff away.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Who knew? Port McNeill, British Columbia, is home to the World’s Largest Burl.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who Am I?</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/20/who-am-i/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Am I?" /><published>2022-07-20T02:01:06+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-20T02:01:06+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/20/who-am-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/20/who-am-i/"><![CDATA[On the Healing Voyage, there are four gauntlets, not including the psychological ones.

First, there’s the Seymour Narrows and Johnstone Strait. This one is particularly tricky. If you don’t get the timing right, the tidal rips are reputed to grab your boat and either suck it into a whirlpool or dash it against the rocks.

We transited the strait without mishap. One down.

Next is the Nahwitti Bar. These are the shallows at the northwest end of the Goletas Channel where ebb currents flowing north meet wind and swell driving south off the open Pacific, creating a “wind over tide” condition. As with the Narrows, it’s very important to cross the bar only at slack water or things could get uncomfortable, even dangerous.

We hit the bar at the perfect time, crossing without a problem. Two down.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0576-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_0576-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0576-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Rounding the Brooks Peninsula
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Rounding the Brooks Peninsula]**
*Original filename: IMG_0576-1024x768.jpg*

Marking the northwestern-most tip of Vancouver Island is Cape Scott. Off Cape Scott, currents swirl, fog thickens, and winds whip. Pick the wrong time to round the cape at your peril.

We rounded Cape Scott under motor in an eight-knot breeze just off the nose and a two-knot flood current only slightly impeding our progress. Three down.

And then there’s the Brooks Peninsula. Like a sore thumb, this ten-mile-long and five-mile-wide landmass sticks out into the Pacific about three-quarters of the way up Vancouver Island’s west coast, forcing boats to go well out to sea to get around it. It makes its own weather, with winds off the peninsula often many times higher than those on adjacent parts of the coast.

In what the Irish describe as a “cracking good sail,” we sailed out and around the peninsula on a broad reach, winds topping out at 27 knots. Four down.

Tonight, we toasted our accomplishment. With all four gauntlets run, we are slowing down, relaxing, and enjoying the rest of the island’s west coast.

Now, please allow me to share some thoughts about one of the psychological “gauntlets” confronting me, the question “Who Am I?”

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0555-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_0555-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0555-1024x768.jpg
Caption: First west coast port of call — Winter Harbour
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: First west coast port of call — Winter Harbour]**
*Original filename: IMG_0555-1024x768.jpg*

Last Memorial Day weekend, I took my first tentative step back out into the world. Only six weeks removed from Jocelyn’s departure and less than a month after her Ceremony of Gratitude, I wasn’t sure I was ready but took the risk.

Jocelyn and I had been invited to the marriage celebration of the daughter of our friends Mark and Sue over Memorial Day weekend at their ranch in southern Colorado. We had planned to attend, but now I just couldn’t see going alone. I wasn’t ready to be social. Besides, how could I, the guy with the very recent sad, sad thing fake being upbeat and fun at a happy, happy weekend party?

I came up with an alternative. My friends John and Jackie had invited me for a camping weekend at their raw land in northern New Mexico. I accepted, knowing it would only be the three of us and that they would honor my circumstances. I decided to stop in at Mark and Sue’s ranch on Friday as I drove down to New Mexico, drop off my gift for the bride and groom, and offer congratulations.

When I got to the ranch, there was already a lot of activity. People were busy getting things set up for the event the next day. Sue greeted me as I arrived. Then I went on a walk around the ranch looking for her daughter to give her my gift.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0594-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_0594-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0594-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Dinghying ashore for a pit stop in the Bunsby Islands
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Dinghying ashore for a pit stop in the Bunsby Islands]**
*Original filename: IMG_0594-768x1024.jpg*

Along the way, I ran into Mark who was busy with preparations. He greeted me and then asked, “Is Jocelyn with you?”

It was as if a stake had been driven through my heart. I looked at him and said, “Yes, she is.”

He instantly realized his gaffe. Looking pale, he said he was sorry. Those witnessing the exchange who knew the truth were visibly stunned.

I knew then that opting out of the weekend was the right thing to do. Soon after, I made my goodbyes and continued south.

How could he have made such a mistake? After all, he had attended Jocelyn’s ceremony less than a month earlier. Obviously, he was wrapped up in his own world, focused on things important to him. And why shouldn’t he be? His daughter was celebrating her marriage.

But for me, it had another meaning. His flub was an example of the world’s obliviousness to my grief. Though my world has been upended, the sun keeps rising each morning. The rest of creation hasn’t noticed my plight.

More than that, it pointed out something else. For nearly 40 years, whenever someone thought of me, they thought of Jocelyn. And whenever someone thought of Jocelyn, they thought of me. We had become one identity. Jack and Jocelyn. Jocelyn and Jack. A package deal.

Now there was only Jack.

How can I go on without my partner, my soulmate, the person who made me complete?

## Who am I now?

My friend Betty is a member of the club I wrote about two blog posts ago. Having suffered the loss of her dear partner, Pat, several years back, she understands.

Following my last blog post, she texted me this:

“’How low can I go?’ This is the question posed in your blog. There will be many low points, some lower than your current state, because this healing does not present itself in a straight upward trajectory.

“The shock and the idealization stages appear to be waning as the anger monkey and self-pity monsters are trying to grab onto your psyche. You are now entering the battle for self-identity. It will be a long hard fight, healthy emotions vs. self-destructive emotions, emotions vs. reason. As you fight this inner battle, remember you do have agency over emotions. You are fighting for the Jack you want to be.

“The question you should put in the forefront of your mind is not ‘How low can I go?’ but ‘What kind of person do I want to be?’ When the anger monkey approaches, ask yourself, ‘Is this the company I want to keep?’”

A week or so after Jocelyn’s ceremony, I decided I could put off reviewing the papers on her desk no longer. She had spoiled me, you see. She took care of everything to do with expenses. In our household, I had very little to do with money (other than making it, of course). As our accountant, she kept track of everything – managed the bills, maintained records of how money came and went.

Now I would have to do all that.

Looking through her in box, I found a past due property tax bill. She had it in her pending file, obviously intending to pay it as soon as she got back from British Columbia. Distracted, I hadn’t noticed it until now.

I took it to the county building the next day along with her death certificate and pled my case. The clerk was really nice. She said there would be no problem. No late fee, nothing. Just pay the bill and all’s well. I was relieved.

But in the process, I had to fill out a form. On the form was an entry for marital status. I had to choke down a lump in my throat when I suddenly realized I would have to check the box “widow.”

Now the world views me differently.

Shortly after my first (virtual) meeting with my grief counselor, she sent me what she called “some useful material.” There was a pdf on the stages of grief. Another one entitled, “Myths of Grief.” One called “Reconciliation Tasks.” And one more, “Who Am I.”

Hesitatingly, I opened each in turn, disbelieving that I was now a student and practitioner of such subject matter.

In the file called Reconciliation Tasks, there is a heading #4: “Develop a new self-identity.” Beneath it, it reads, “Part of who you are was formed by the relationship you had with the person who is gone. The way you defined yourself and the way society defines you has changed. Re-anchor yourself, reconstruct your self-identity. This is long, hard work.”

Opening the “Who Am I” file, I found a lengthy series of questions intended to elicit self-assessment. Here are a few examples:

What were the three most positive events of your childhood? The three most negative?

What is one specific situation where you feel angry or frustrated?

## What period of your life did you like the most?

## What types of people do you enjoy spending time with?

And so on.

This grief business just got more complicated. Not only am I grieving the loss of the love of my life, now to go on I have to reconstruct my identity?

As if tears, rage, anguish, loneliness, and inexpressible sadness weren’t enough, now add fear to the list.

That’s the overriding emotion when I think about the “work” of building a new self-identity. To do so requires looking deep within, recognizing the good but, perhaps more saliently, confronting the bad. Prodding demons out of hiding so they can be confronted and conquered. Slaying dragons that corrupt my psyche.

Demons and dragons. Terrifying.

I suppose I could procrastinate. I’m not sure I want the Healing Voyage to take this turn quite yet. One step at a time.

In September, I’ve enrolled in a five-day silent meditation retreat at a place called the Gaia House in Devon, United Kingdom. The theme of the retreat is Healing After Loss. Perhaps that is the time and place to tackle self-identity reconstruction. Until then, baby steps.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On the Healing Voyage, there are four gauntlets, not including the psychological ones.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Limbo</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/13/limbo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Limbo" /><published>2022-07-13T23:41:33+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-13T23:41:33+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/13/limbo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/13/limbo/"><![CDATA[## “How low can you go?”

That’s the common chant for spectators of the popular Caribbean game of limbo, urging contestants to bend backwards lower and lower as they shimmy forward under the bar.

That same question haunts my current state.

First, inconsolable grief and sadness. Now COVID? What other misfortune awaits? How low must I go?

Two days after my brother succumbed to COVID I tested positive, symptoms undeniable. Now we had two COVID patients! I resolved to isolate on board, postponing departure from Vancouver for as long as necessary. The Healing Voyage would have to wait.

Feelings of frustration and anger rushed in. How could this have happened? Why didn’t Bill take better precautions? He told me he didn’t even wear a mask on the plane! The anger mingled with my daily staple of sadness and desperation since Jocelyn left.

Perhaps all of this is some sort of test. What does it take to drive Jack over the edge?

Consider what I was dealing with. Death of a loved one. A known deadly virus. How do I survive these tests?

As I wrote in my anniversary card to Jocelyn, this grieving business is the hardest thing I’ve ever done. The deep, inexpressible sadness of missing her is helped, though, by the people who have connected with me. Particularly in the first weeks after Jocelyn died, many offered condolences and support. As grief took hold, the attention was always welcome and well meaning.

Invariably, they’d ask me, concern in their voices, “How are you doing?”

This greeting, routine in normal circumstances, struck me as oddly insensitive in those first days of full-fledged shock. In my head, the reply that instantly formed was “How the f*** do you think I’m doing?” I kept that to myself of course, instead saying, “As you might imagine.”

As one contact followed another over the next week or so – each opening with the same question, “How ya’ doing?” – my response evolved into “That’s a dumb question.” Overhearing that reply, my son admonished me, saying it was rude and off putting. My friend Roni suggested I reply with “I think I’ll be okay” as a way of easing folks’ worries about my state of mind, even if it wasn’t completely true. You see, I did then and continue now to worry about whether I will ever be able to be happy again. That’s the power of this grief thing.

As the bouts of rage, anguish, and tears accumulated, a revelation dawned on me. I was experiencing something quintessentially human. This level of suffering, this grieving, is a uniquely human experience. I’ve read of corollaries in the animal world (elephants, for example) but on this scale? Surely not. A new reply formed to the question “How are you doing?” It was “Well, I’m not getting cheated out of a full dose of humanity.”

After the standard greeting of “How are you doing?” the next question often was “What are you going to do now?” As a reflection of the grip grief had (has?) on me, I would reply, “I’ve got a new full-time job. It’s very demanding. 24/7 actually.”

“Oh. What is it?” they would ask.

“Grieving widower,” came the reply.

I suppose my son might categorize my part in this exchange as a bit off putting as well because it often elicited pained expressions, an anxious chuckle, or an abrupt end to the conversation.

The flip side of these many early connections is the absence of contact by more than a few people who I would have thought would be concerned about me, or at least would want to check in with me in my suffering.

As the days turned into weeks, I encountered a person or two who fit this category. Awkwardly, they would offer an explanation for not contacting me such as “I thought you would want your privacy” or “I didn’t want to intrude” as if I needed to be left alone in my suffering.

David Kessler, who helped develop the five stages of grief and authored _Finding Meaning: The Sixth Stage of Grief_ , writes that isolation is no antidote for a grieving person. The opposite, in fact. To be effective, grief needs to be witnessed, he asserts, because we are all social creatures who need connection and affirmation.

My theory is that, rather than concern for me, those avoiding me are subconsciously avoiding the subject matter at hand, namely suffering and death. Now, I am stigmatized, the embodiment of suffering, a person recently acquainted with death. It is understandable that I should be avoided. Nothing personal. Just a reality. Who wants to be reminded of their own frailty and mortality?

Kessler: “We want to ignore death, forget it, deny it. But it will come to all of us. It’s the change that happens whether we want it to or not. If met head-on, the prospect of death, its inevitability, can bring new meaning to life.”

Perhaps the way to pass this test is to find new meaning. Rather than avoid the subject of suffering and death, don’t necessarily dwell on it, but accept it and use it as a spring board for good.

Just as when my children were born, Jocelyn’s passing has caused me to see things differently. Life suddenly has more value, is more precious now. More finite, to be sure. Perhaps part of the way forward, the solution to this test, is to recognize the gift each day presents, to take nothing for granted, to live life as intentionally as possible.

From birth, we are programmed to strive. Instinct drives us to seek nourishment, to connect, to survive. The catch phrase for surviving grief is “one day at a time; heck, one hour at a time.” As hours turn into days and days into weeks, the instinct to put one foot in front of the other, to seek a new path, reveals. The path forward never forgets the loved one who is gone. Rather, it honors her, becomes part of her legacy as it is followed by someone who lives life deeply influenced by her, and seeks to live well, as she would want.

Bill stayed in his bunk in the V-berth for two days. At its peak his fever hit 101.7 degrees Fahrenheit. I ministered to him with soup and tea. He emerged on day three feeling somewhat better though not entirely well, just as I slipped into symptoms. Mine weren’t as bad as feared perhaps because, unlike him, I had received a recent second vaccine booster shot. At its worst I experienced what I would characterize as a bad head cold.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0375-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_0375-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0375-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Vancouver skyline from Coal Harbour Marina.
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Vancouver skyline from Coal Harbour Marina.]**
*Original filename: IMG_0375-1024x768.jpg*

Considering our setbacks, I admitted the possibility of sacrificing my goal of circumnavigating Vancouver Island. Once the fog of COVID began to lift, Bill urged that we stick to the plan. We would leapfrog ahead, making up for lost time. The only sacrifice would be our time in Vancouver, which was limited to the view of downtown from the end of the dock.

On Friday, July 8th, we motored under the Lions Gate bridge, leaving Vancouver in our wake. Our course took us north and west, up the Sunshine Coast and through the Johnstone Strait toward the top of the island.

How low can he go? All the way to the bottom. From there, there is nowhere to go but up.

The Healing Voyage had resumed.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“How low can you go?”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Healing Voyage</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/06/the-healing-voyage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Healing Voyage" /><published>2022-07-06T23:19:32+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-06T23:19:32+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/06/the-healing-voyage</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/07/06/the-healing-voyage/"><![CDATA[## What needs healing?

## A. A wound?

## B. Pain?

## C. Trauma?

## D. All of the above?

If you chose Answer D, you are correct.

## And how does one heal?

## A. Time?

## B. Attitude?

## C. Sharing love?

## D. All of the above (and more)?

Again, it’s Answer D.

This voyage – I’m calling it the Healing Voyage – is intended to provide time and space for grieving, for remembering, for honoring, and for sharing the love I have for Jocelyn.

Unlike past seasons, when this blog served mainly to record the people, places, and experiences had aboard the _Windleblo_ , now this space offers more. Yes, it will continue to record the when and the where of my watery wanderings, but now it can serve to help me heal.

Given the blow I have suffered, I suspect there’s no way to keep my feelings out of these pages. So why not let go? Allow emotion to color my vision. Explore what that means for now and tomorrow. Together, we’ll see where it leads.

Before we start, a word about privacy. You may wonder, why is he posting these innermost thoughts on his blog? After all, it’s very public. Anyone can find it, read it.

Under the circumstances I now find myself in, I decided it was okay to seek grief counseling. Among other things, my counselor advised that many people find writing helpful in processing grief. I’ve also discovered that the people I feel most comfortable talking to about my grief are people who have been there, people who have suffered a loss of their own in the past. For their willingness to listen – and to respond lovingly, without judgement – I am forever grateful.

These folks form a kind of club. An unwelcome one to be sure, but none-the-less a group bound by common experience. Members of this club are good at paying it forward by helping newcomers to the club with their grief.

When thinking about whether to keep my writings private or posting them on the blog, I considered that posting could be my own way of paying it forward. Perhaps readers could relate to their own experience, or at least empathize with mine. As I’ve learned recently, there are only two kinds of people in this world – those who have grieved and those who will. I decided if I could I should help whoever is coping with what I am coping with now. I decided to put the writings on the blog.

And then there’s the question of What Would Jocelyn Do.

Before Jocelyn’s Ceremony of Gratitude, I ordered a bunch of WWJD bracelets off Amazon. At the risk of offending devout Christians, I co-opted the acronym for my own meaning – What Would Jocelyn Do? She had a knack for knowing the right choice in most any situation, plus her ethics met the gold standard, so I accepted her way a lot. I distributed the bracelets to closest friends and family who knew her best and would understand the meaning. For now, I wear the bracelet every day to help me find my way.

Jocelyn wasn’t a writer. She was an accountant, more of a numbers person. And she was all about helping others. If a choice presented itself to her where one way would help others more than another, she would take the more helping way. If these pages can help anyone turn their grief into love, then she would be all for it.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IMG_0346-1024x768.jpeg
Filename: IMG_0346-1024x768.jpeg
Date path: 2022/07/IMG_0346-1024x768.jpeg
Caption: Skipper and mascot upon tying up at Royal Vancouver Yacht Club
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Skipper and mascot upon tying up at Royal Vancouver Yacht Club]**
*Original filename: IMG_0346-1024x768.jpeg*

So the Healing Voyage has begun. On July 4th, my crew and I set sail from Canoe Cove Marina, North Saanich, British Columbia. The crew consists of myself as skipper, my brother Bill as first mate, and my dog Frida as mascot.

Our loose cruising plan is to head north and possibly circumnavigate Vancouver Island. Our first sail took us about 40 nautical miles north to a berth in the Royal Vancouver Yacht Club at Coal Harbour, right in downtown Vancouver.

Allow me now to pose the question again.

## How does one heal?

Well, certainly not by inflicting more pain and suffering.

That’s why when Bill tested positive for COVID the day after we arrived in Vancouver, our Healing Voyage took a detour.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What needs healing?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The World Ends</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/06/29/the-world-ends/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World Ends" /><published>2022-06-29T06:24:28+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-29T06:24:28+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/06/29/the-world-ends</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/06/29/the-world-ends/"><![CDATA[From the _Windleblo_ log, 1300 hours, April 16, 2022: “The world ends. 048.11072N, 122.751419W.”

That’s the entry that records the time and place of my beloved First and Only Mate’s departure from this world.

On April 16th, my world ended when Jocelyn collapsed into my arms in the cockpit of the _Windleblo_ as we were preparing lines and fenders for docking at the Port Townsend Boat Haven. Totally unexpected, it was a queen’s death, her light shining as bright as ever one minute, gone the next. It was Easter Sunday when her spirit soared from its earthly bonds.

Much has transpired since that moment. My children and I brought her home to Colorado. We produced a ceremony of gratitude as beautiful as she. We witnessed both grief and love evolve among family, friends, and community.

Now, I have returned to the _Windleblo_ for a summer cruise just as Jocelyn and I have done for years. This time, I am calling it a “healing voyage.” I alternate between confidence and trepidation that this is the right next step for me.

Thirty-seven years ago today, I made Jocelyn my wife. To commemorate the occasion, today I sent Jocelyn an anniversary card. Here is the message I wrote inside:

## “Wife-

Today is our 37th wedding anniversary and this is the anniversary card from your husband. As in past years, the salutation is simply “wife” and it is simply signed “husband.” Though that might seem impersonal, I know for you it’s unmistakable who it’s to and who it came from. For more than 36 years those terms have defined us.

The difference this year is your address. I am entrusting delivery of this card to the Canadian postal service. It is addressed to you, c/o God, in Heaven, because if you are reachable, I know that’s where you must be.

I won’t lie. Since you left, I have been a mess. Not knowing what else to do, I resolved to return to the boat this summer to go sailing just as you and I have for more than a decade. I arrived in British Columbia yesterday with Frida as my companion after a three-day drive from Colorado.

While on the road, I listened to a couple of books on tape that I downloaded using your Audible account. The books I chose are about what I am going through now, which is an extraordinary dose of grief at your departure from this world. They say the depth of your grief is equal to the depth of your love for the person you lost. If that is so, then I must have loved you very, very much.

One of the hopeful things I’ve learned from the books I listened to is that as all the sadness, pain, and suffering subsides a huge reservoir of love appears. Once I emerge from my grief, our love can combine us once again just as when you were alive. But for now, I must endure what I know to be the hardest thing I have ever done.

I know that when we came to the boat in April you were so close to finally casting off the tethers that held you to your commitments to others. You were just about to start doing all the things you wanted to do. The solo walkabout in Scotland you booked for yourself this September was to mark that transition.

Well, the kids and I have pledged to take you on that walkabout. We have spoken with Nathan at Celtic Trails and he has arranged for us to walk the very same route to St. Andrews that you chose. You will be with us as we do.

I think of you constantly, always with love in my heart, wondering if you can feel it. By now I expect you’ve made quite a few friends there, what with everyone falling in love with you the minute they meet you. Please tell them I envy how lucky they are to have you with them now.

1.4.3.

## Husband”

End Note: I grew up and learned how to sail in Cohasset, Massachusetts. Just outside Cohasset harbor is Minots Ledge. Many a ship grounded and wrecked on Minots Ledge until a lighthouse was built there in 1850. As with all lighthouses, Minots has a signature light pattern. It blinks once, then, after a pause, four times, then another pause, and finally three times. Local lore has it that the one-four-three pattern stands for I LOVE YOU. Since I’ve known her, I’ve used this shorthand in closing many notes and letters to Jocelyn.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From the Windleblo log, 1300 hours, April 16, 2022: “The world ends. 048.11072N, 122.751419W.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022 Windleblo Cruising Plan</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/01/14/2022-windleblo-cruising-plan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022 Windleblo Cruising Plan" /><published>2022-01-14T18:39:10+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-14T18:39:10+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/01/14/2022-windleblo-cruising-plan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2022/01/14/2022-windleblo-cruising-plan/"><![CDATA[Well, there’s still a lot of mostly COVID-related uncertainty about how the year’s going to unfold. But you know what they say about plans — they are a basis for change.

For the first time, we’re excited to conceive a season without any pressure to make miles. The theme this year is to explore our new home waters, the Salish Sea. To help us do that, we’ve joined the Port Townsend Yacht Club and plan to tag along on their “Flex Cruise” to the Broughton Islands during the heart of the season.

Other than that, we’ll stay flexible and let wind and waves (and whim) set our course.

So here’s the sketch. 

March – April: Spring Commissioning at Canoe Cove Marina, North Saanich, BC; Shake down cruise to Port Townsend.

May – June: Travel by car from Golden to North Saanich. Begin inaugural exploration from Canoe Cove into the Salish Sea.

July – August: Shore leave during busy season for family reunion in Windleblo Cove, Lake Winnipesaukee, New Hampshire.

September – October: Return by car to S/V Windleblo for a month of continued adventuring in the Salish Sea.

November: Fall decommissioning, Canoe Cove.

Stay tuned for updates as the goal posts move.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Well, there’s still a lot of mostly COVID-related uncertainty about how the year’s going to unfold. But you know what they say about plans — they are a basis for change.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Crossing</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/08/21/the-crossing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crossing" /><published>2021-08-21T15:30:08+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-21T15:30:08+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/08/21/the-crossing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/08/21/the-crossing/"><![CDATA[You get a little crazy on an ocean crossing. Whether it’s the constant motion, the monotony, sleep deprivation, close quarters, the raw power of the ocean, or something else I’m not sure. But by the end of the voyage, a brand of giddiness sets in that infects most everyone.

This voyage started with craziness.

Emily safely home, a new strong crew showed up in Ketchikan – John Hoopes and John Renna. My given name is also John. (Most Jacks are actually Johns don’t you know.) So we had a crew of Johns on this voyage.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/IMG_2231-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_2231-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2021/08/IMG_2231-scaled.jpg
Caption: Sunrise off the top of Vancouver Island
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Sunrise off the top of Vancouver Island]**
*Original filename: IMG_2231-scaled.jpg*

We needed crazy voyage names to make things easier. John Renna would now be known as John Reno, or Reno for short. John Hoopes would become Johnny Donut, an internet alias he has occasionally used as a riff on John Doe. I would go by Cap, short for captain. (Not that cray cray, I know, but what can I say?)

As usual, the wind made the decision easy on when to go. A five-day weather window would open starting the day after the new crew’s arrival, just long enough for the 600-nautical-mile passage to Port Townsend, Washington. After a day or so of light wind, moderate to strong breezes would line up behind the beam the rest of the way. Perfect! Then the window would slam shut with southerlies and snotty weather returning to Southeast Alaska and the BC coast.

We had to jump through that window.

We toyed with the alternative of floating around the Southeast for a week waiting for Canada to open up. Ottawa had just announced new rules allowing U.S. travelers to enter Canada starting August 9th provided they were fully vaccinated and recently tested COVID negative. But the Council of the Haida Nation had not yet followed suit, keeping Haida Gwaii, the most appealing stop on the way south, out of bounds. Plus, waiting a week would require a new weather window to open, which did not look likely. We resolved to go now, leaving Haida Gwaii for another season.

But first, we had 24-hours to bond. It started with a delicious baked pasta dish washed down with red wine on the evening of the crew’s arrival. It continued the next day with a forest hike above town, a rejuvenating pint at the Bawden Street brewery, a touristy walk down Creek Street, and a satisfying meal at the New York Café, all before returning to the boat by 4 pm.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/IMG_1790-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_1790-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/08/IMG_1790-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Leaving Dall Bay
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Leaving Dall Bay]**
*Original filename: IMG_1790-1024x768.jpg*

Before shoving off, I assigned tasks to the crew to help them get oriented. They performed a rig check, inspected and familiarized themselves with their PFDs, and identified the location of all the fire extinguishers and bilge pumps on board. We then met in the cockpit to talk about what they found and review the weather forecast and passage plan. I emphasized three personal responsibilities to promote a successful crossing – nutrition, hydration, and prostration; if each of us made sure to keep ourselves nourished, hydrated, and well-rested, the chances of our success would go up. After then talking about the sequence for casting off, we left the dock close to 5 pm.

Rather than blast off right away, I thought it best to give the crew a night swinging at anchor. Thirteen nautical miles south of Ketchikan, we entered Dall Bay and proceeded to a quiet cove at the head of the bay. A whale greeted us as she fed at the cove’s mouth and bald eagles circled overhead, a fitting finale for our time in Alaska. _Windleblo_ swung serenely at anchor through the night, rock solid as we slumbered.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/DSC_0059-1024x678.jpg
Filename: DSC_0059-1024x678.jpg
Date path: 2021/08/DSC_0059-1024x678.jpg
Caption: Croatian brandy offering to Neptune
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Croatian brandy offering to Neptune]**
*Original filename: DSC_0059-1024x678.jpg*

Before weighing anchor the next morning, we gathered on the foredeck at 0600 to petition Neptune for a safe crossing. Reno led the recitations, entreating the seven directions on our behalf. A dram of Croatian brandy went to Neptune, along with a dram each down our gullets.

Ceremony complete, our voyage started in earnest. As predicted, light winds prevailed at first, some on the nose but less than 10 knots, not enough to bother. We soon escaped the confines of the Anderson Archipelago, open ocean to starboard, happy to ride a smooth sea with half meter swell. As the mountains on Prince of Wales Island receded, the winds picked up and shifted west giving us a glorious beam reach across the Dixon Entrance. Only the occasional deadhead log made our way a bit tricky. As day turned into night, we watched Rose Point at the northeast corner of Haida Gwaii slide past our starboard beam, frustrated that COVID restrictions meant we could not make landfall on these alluring islands. We entered Hecate Strait.

Often, crossing Hecate Strait at night is a hair-raising experience. Johnny Donut read in one of our Haida Gwaii reference books that “Hecate Strait is reputed to be one of the roughest stretches of water on the Pacific Ocean,” largely because it is relatively shallow and wind over tide conditions can create huge short steep waves. Our weather window did not betray us, though, and we motored on flat seas under cloudy skies. Solo two-hour watches kept us on track through our first night at sea. By dawn we had well surpassed our first hundred nautical miles, grateful for not having collided during the night with any of the many logs we saw floating in the strait during daylight, sometimes entire trees, roots and all.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/IMG_2219-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_2219-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/08/IMG_2219-1024x768.jpg
Caption: One of many logs we dodged in Hecate Strait
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: One of many logs we dodged in Hecate Strait]**
*Original filename: IMG_2219-1024x768.jpg*

Early on Day Two, August 1, 2021, I noticed an error code on the Mastervolt battery monitor indicating that the batteries were overheating. As a precaution, the monitor had automatically interrupted charging. Immediately, I switched off the engine and investigated. Thankfully the wind was starting to fill in behind us and we continued to make decent way under sail. Exposing the battery box confirmed the error code. The batteries were indeed very hot to the touch. I increased ventilation to the box and vowed to keep the engine switched off as much as possible the rest of the way, operating only enough to maintain charge once the batteries cooled. I already knew the batteries were on their last legs; this added greater impetus to replace them ASAP.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/IMG_1882-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_1882-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/08/IMG_1882-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Enchiladas for dinner courtesy of Johnny Reno
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Enchiladas for dinner courtesy of Johnny Reno]**
*Original filename: IMG_1882-768x1024.jpg*

It was easy to tell when we left Hecate Strait. Deep blue water and steady one meter swell on our starboard quarter told us we were entering open ocean. A cloudless sky completed the blue panorama. Fifty nautical miles offshore now, we were as far from land as this crossing would take us. A consistent ten to twelve knots of wind slightly behind the starboard beam allowed us to break out the gennaker and bust along at seven knots through the water. Life was very good indeed. Fish chowder for dinner took top honors as the best meal of the passage. At midnight, the milky way was stunningly vivid, punctuated occasionally by shooting stars. A waxing gibbous moon rose as a crescent shining over the wee-est hours before dawn.

By Day Three, we were well into the rhythms of a sea crossing. The motion of the boat seemed pleasing, symptoms of sleep deprivation crept in, and the routines of running the boat kept us occupied. Foremost among these was adjusting the sails to suit the conditions. As the wind freshened and backed behind us, we exercised our deck skills setting up the whisker pole to run wing-on-wing. Off the top of Vancouver Island, the wind died. Headsail furled and boom pinned to the centerline, we switched on the motor. Listening to the VHF weather, a gale warning was posted for later in the day and into the night. A satphone call to Jocelyn confirmed the forecast. Twenty-five to thirty-five knot winds from the northwest were forecast through the night.

The dead air we were now motoring through appeared to be the calm before the storm.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/IMG_2233-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_2233-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/08/IMG_2233-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Deck work preparing for the gale
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Deck work preparing for the gale]**
*Original filename: IMG_2233-768x1024.jpg*

By mid-afternoon, the promised winds began to build. I thought about shrinking the sails down as the winds rose, but then decided to break out the staysail from deep in the hold. It had not seen daylight for several seasons and needed airing out. As the sun set, we secured the removable stay to the strong point in the middle of the foredeck, furled the genoa, reefed the main, and hanked on the staysail. Tidying up below secured anything loose. We were ready for the gale.

Two-meter breaking waves on our starboard quarter shoved the transom around. The winds rose steadily as night fell and brilliant stars emerged. We rotated through our watchkeeping schedule. By morning, it was clear we had dodged a bullet. The highest observed gust was only in the high twenties, the seas moderate. As daylight took hold, we put away the staysail, raised the whisker pole, and went back to wing-on-wing. Gawking at the glory of the Vancouver Island mountain landscape to port, we cursed COVID for frustrating our intentions to explore this coast.

As we approached the Straits of Juan de Fuca, it seemed most of our work was complete. Five hundred nautical miles had been logged. Protected waters spread before us. But fully twenty percent of the voyage remained. To remind us that we were not yet done, the winds again died and a foggy drizzle enveloped us. We soldiered on through the cold damp, hugging the Canadian side of the strait to avoid foul currents and stay out of the shipping lanes.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/IMG_2218-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_2218-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/08/IMG_2218-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Fog in the Straits of Juan de Fuca
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Fog in the Straits of Juan de Fuca]**
*Original filename: IMG_2218-1024x768.jpg*

Our fourth night at sea began shrouded in fog. Initially motoring, the wind returned, again right behind us. We had kept the whisker pole up, so it was a simple matter of unfurling the genoa to resume sailing. At the 1 am watch change, we furled the headsail, jibed the boat, and turned ninety degrees to starboard to cross the Traffic Separation Scheme at a right angle. Once across, we turned downwind and resumed our easterly heading, now under full sail with a fresh breeze. As day broke, fog returned. Port Townsend lay just ahead.

Rounding Point Wilson, we entered Port Townsend as the fog burned off. Hailing the port authorities, we were assigned slip C178 in the Boat Haven. Bright blue sky greeted us as we glided into the slip, our voyage complete.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/IMG_2257-1-1024x769.jpg
Filename: IMG_2257-1-1024x769.jpg
Date path: 2021/08/IMG_2257-1-1024x769.jpg
Caption: Victory beers in Port Townsend!
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Victory beers in Port Townsend!]**
*Original filename: IMG_2257-1-1024x769.jpg*

A jubilating giddiness enveloped the crew as we relished our accomplishment. Five days at sea and the boat had been moved from its Alaskan adventure ground to its new home waters. We could now relax, knowing our goal was reached. Next was food, beers, hot showers, and sleep.

Over beers, I asked the Johns to give me five words each that captured their sense of the voyage. Here is what they said. Reno: Epic, Challenging, Teamwork, Ordered Disruption, Awe Inspiring. Johnny Donut: Delightfully Uneventful, Too Short, Trance-like/Entrancing, Nostalgic, Humbling/Whales.

Not too crazy, but a fitting summation of a smooth crossing.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You get a little crazy on an ocean crossing. Whether it’s the constant motion, the monotony, sleep deprivation, close quarters, the raw power of the ocean, or something else I’m not sure. But by the end of the voyage, a brand of giddiness sets in that infects most everyone.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leg Two Report: Sitka to Ketchikan</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/07/29/leg-two-report-sitka-to-ketchikan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leg Two Report: Sitka to Ketchikan" /><published>2021-07-29T06:10:23+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-29T06:10:23+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/07/29/leg-two-report-sitka-to-ketchikan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/07/29/leg-two-report-sitka-to-ketchikan/"><![CDATA[Shore leave over, daughter Emily joined me in Sitka for a modified Leg Two, Sitka to Ketchikan. We had 10 days to cover 260 nautical miles, taking in a return (for me) to Warm Springs, marine wildlife at Tebenkof Bay, the raw solitude of Coronation Island, and a half circumnavigation of Prince of Wales Island.

I asked Emily to select her favorite photos of the voyage. Here’s what she picked:

## A close encounter, flukes and all!

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2545-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_2545-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2545-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Alongside the Warm Springs dock
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Alongside the Warm Springs dock]**
*Original filename: IMG_2545-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2549-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_2549-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2549-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Ahhhh…bathhouse near the dock at Warm Springs
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Ahhhh…bathhouse near the dock at Warm Springs]**
*Original filename: IMG_2549-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2586-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_2586-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2586-768x1024.jpg
Caption: The boardwalk to the hot springs
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: The boardwalk to the hot springs]**
*Original filename: IMG_2586-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2568-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_2568-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2568-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Hot springs pool
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Hot springs pool]**
*Original filename: IMG_2568-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2560-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_2560-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2560-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Cold plunge in Baranof Lake
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Cold plunge in Baranof Lake]**
*Original filename: IMG_2560-1024x768.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2605-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_2605-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2605-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Mossy hike on Coronation Island
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Mossy hike on Coronation Island]**
*Original filename: IMG_2605-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2615-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_2615-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2615-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Wing on wing heading north up Sumner Strait
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Wing on wing heading north up Sumner Strait]**
*Original filename: IMG_2615-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2628-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_2628-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2628-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Community skiff repair dock in Point Baker, a small fishing village on the northwest tip of Prince of Wales Island
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Community skiff repair dock in Point Baker, a small fishing village on the northwest tip of Prince of Wales Island]**
*Original filename: IMG_2628-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_9482-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_9482-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_9482-scaled.jpg
Caption: Looking out the port hole at our fishing boat neighbors in Casey Moran harbor, Ketchikan
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Looking out the port hole at our fishing boat neighbors in Casey Moran harbor, Ketchikan]**
*Original filename: IMG_9482-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_9477-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9477-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_9477-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Deer Mountain trail near Ketchikan. We climbed from sea level to 1,500 feet.
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Deer Mountain trail near Ketchikan. We climbed from sea level to 1,500 feet.]**
*Original filename: IMG_9477-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2585-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_2585-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2585-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Temperate rain forest vegetation alongside the trail
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Temperate rain forest vegetation alongside the trail]**
*Original filename: IMG_2585-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2678-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_2678-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2678-scaled.jpg
Caption: Looking upslope, Deer Mountain trail
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Looking upslope, Deer Mountain trail]**
*Original filename: IMG_2678-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_9496-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9496-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_9496-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Steps on a drizzly night leading down to the Married Man’s Trail, Ketchikan
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Steps on a drizzly night leading down to the Married Man’s Trail, Ketchikan]**
*Original filename: IMG_9496-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2661-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_2661-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2661-scaled.jpg
Caption: Pilings holding up one of Ketchikan’s best watering holes at low tide. Viewed from the Casey Moran docks.
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Pilings holding up one of Ketchikan’s best watering holes at low tide. Viewed from the Casey Moran docks.]**
*Original filename: IMG_2661-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_2657-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_2657-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_2657-scaled.jpg
Caption: One of many fish restaurants, Ketchikan
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: One of many fish restaurants, Ketchikan]**
*Original filename: IMG_2657-scaled.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_9478-1-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9478-1-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_9478-1-1024x768.jpg
Caption: The first post-COVID cruise ship to visit Ketchikan. Notice the paddleboarder in front of the ship.
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: The first post-COVID cruise ship to visit Ketchikan. Notice the paddleboarder in front of the ship.]**
*Original filename: IMG_9478-1-1024x768.jpg*

All in all, a very fun successful cruise.

While we were at it, Canada announced intentions to admit vaccinated Americans into their country starting August 9th. Unfortunately, it does not appear the Council of the Haida Nation will follow suit, so we will have to forego a visit to Gwaii Haanas for now.

So of necessity we are modifying the 2021 Cruising Plan as we go. Our new Plan A is to head offshore for a 5-night bluewater cruise from Ketchikan to Port Townsend, WA, never touching Canada. Watching now for a weather window. Son John and good friend John Renna arrive tomorrow for the crossing. Soon, the last of southeast Alaska for the Windleblo in 2021 will be in the log books.

Stay tuned.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Shore leave over, daughter Emily joined me in Sitka for a modified Leg Two, Sitka to Ketchikan. We had 10 days to cover 260 nautical miles, taking in a return (for me) to Warm Springs, marine wildlife at Tebenkof Bay, the raw solitude of Coronation Island, and a half circumnavigation of Prince of Wales Island.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sitka</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/07/15/sitka/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sitka" /><published>2021-07-15T04:41:46+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-15T04:41:46+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/07/15/sitka</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/07/15/sitka/"><![CDATA[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG-5679.jpg
Filename: IMG-5679.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG-5679.jpg
Caption: Neptune Lives!
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Neptune Lives!]**
*Original filename: IMG-5679.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_9455-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9455-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_9455-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Sitka waterfront
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Sitka waterfront]**
*Original filename: IMG_9455-1024x768.jpg*

We arrived in Sitka with a few days to explore before our shore leave back to Colorado. Upon arrival, the harbormaster put us on the “A float” in Old Thomsen Harbor where we quickly met Rob, owner of S/V _Chantey_ , who oriented us to the neighborhood. He even offered us the use of his car to run errands, which immediately vaulted him into the “friendly native” category.

Looking around, the docks were abuzz with activity. Part of the salmon season opened in a few days, and the harbor was jammed with fishing boats gearing up for the catch. Just like the other towns in the Southeast, Sitka is all about fishing and here was ample evidence. Boat after boat was loading up on equipment, provisions, bait, and ice as crews assembled for departure. Then, as if a starting gun sounded, the boats vanished leaving the harbor much quieter.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_9436-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9436-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_9436-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Fortress of the Bears
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Fortress of the Bears]**
*Original filename: IMG_9436-1024x768.jpg*

Exploring the town, Jocelyn found a shop where she learned about harvesting salt from the sea. She came away with several pouches of salt, some with exotic flavors, to share as gifts. Later, we broke out the Bromptons and rode six miles out of town to a bear sanctuary called Fortress of the Bears where orphaned cubs were saved and raised to adulthood. But the highlight of our time in Sitka was celebrating our 36th wedding anniversary by enjoying a fine meal at Ludwig’s Bistro, which everyone said was the best restaurant in town. We agreed.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/IMG_9466-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9466-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/07/IMG_9466-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Rob and Zach at the Mash Tun
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Rob and Zach at the Mash Tun]**
*Original filename: IMG_9466-1024x768.jpg*

On July 2nd, Alaska Airlines carried us away from Sitka. Returning July 13th, I found _Windleblo_ as I left her, sitting pretty in the water ready for action. I spent a day provisioning and got to join Rob for a beautiful four-mile hike to Beaver Lake in the hills south of town, capped off by a beer at Harbor Mountain Brewery, complete with a tour of the brewery operation by the owner Zach.

Next, Emily joins for the Leg Two of the season, a cruise from Sitka to Ketchikan.]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Baranof</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/06/29/baranof/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baranof" /><published>2021-06-29T04:49:50+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-29T04:49:50+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/06/29/baranof</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/06/29/baranof/"><![CDATA[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9379-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9379-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9379-1024x768.jpg
Caption: 
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ]**
*Original filename: IMG_9379-1024x768.jpg*

I’d been intending to arrive in Hoonah for years.

My first intention formed after reading an account in one of the sailing magazines about a boat that laid up for the winter there several years ago. Hoonah is one of the few places around here with a proper marina and Travelift to haul boats and its position as the gateway to Glacier Bay seemed ideal for launching the following season. I first contacted Andy Gray, the Hoonah harbormaster, in May 2018 to explore the idea and he was most welcoming. So for a long time Plan A was to sail to Hoonah and leave _Windleblo_ there for a winter.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9431-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9431-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9431-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Totems
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Totems]**
*Original filename: IMG_9431-768x1024.jpg*

But then I met Ginny Ware, Reed Hranac’s college friend, who grew up in Petersburg. She connected me with the nice people there and I was drawn to that place. Hoonah would have to wait. COVID further intervened to force a delay in my arrival. Now, finally, our intention to arrive in Hoonah would come true.

Leaving Glacier Bay, the wind picked up as we rounded Point Gustavus and headed southeast across Icy Strait. Ten knots, then 15, then 20 on the nose, plus a contrary ebb current, made the 20 nautical miles to Hoonah a slog. Maybe Neptune was trying one last pitch at delaying our visit. As we rounded Cannery Point, though, the seas subsided and the winds calmed for the home stretch into Hoonah.

This is the place where the Tlingit people settled after being chased from Glacier Bay by ice. For generations, the four clans that now comprise the Huna Tlingit – the Chookaneidi, Kaagwaantaan, T’akdeintaan, and Wooshkeetaan – occupied a glacial valley called S’e Shuyee in what is now Glacier Bay National Park. In the mid-1700s as the Little Ice Age progressed, a large glacier at the head of their permanent village site there advanced suddenly and destroyed the village, expelling the four clans. The clans dispersed throughout the Icy Strait area, eventually settling in Hoonah, which translates in the Tlingit language to “protected from the north wind.”

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9372-2-1024x516.jpg
Filename: IMG_9372-2-1024x516.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9372-2-1024x516.jpg
Caption: Hoonah burns
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Hoonah burns]**
*Original filename: IMG_9372-2-1024x516.jpg*

As ever, fishing dominates the Tlingit’s economic history. A cannery was built in Hoonah in 1912 operating until 1953. In 1944, a fire destroyed the town. Some residents were smoking sockeye salmon on an unusually hot windy day. A house caught fire and the fire quickly spread. The town had no fire department. Virtually every dwelling burned. After the fire, most of the residents sheltered at the cannery. World War II housing units bound for Hawaii were diverted to Hoonah by the Coast Guard. These houses, located in the downtown area, are still called “war homes.” A sawmill was built in town in the 1990’s, diversifying Hoonah’s commerce. In 2004, along with the new marina, the town built a cruise ship dock. Tourism suddenly vaulted to the top of the economy except most recently when COVID forced a cruise ship hiatus.

Despite intentions of making Hoonah a focal point of our time in the Southeast, we ended up only spending two nights there, which would have to be enough. We pushed on, this time to one of the highlights of the month’s cruise – Warm Springs Bay and the tiny settlement of Baranof.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9395-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9395-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9395-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Hot springs up the hill next to the river
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Hot springs up the hill next to the river]**
*Original filename: IMG_9395-768x1024.jpg*

The southerlies were forecast to build, along with three days of rain, compelling us to push on 75 nautical miles in one day, arriving in Warm Springs Bay around 1700 hours on June 22nd. Too many boats were tied to the float at the head of the bay for us to fit, so we anchored in an adjacent cove for a comfortable night. At 0900 the next morning, we motored over to the float to find many of the boats departing. We took a spot.

Soon after, we ascended the ramp to find boardwalks leading to public bath houses and natural hot springs all fed by gorgeous geothermally heated water springing from the hillside above. Making the setting particularly enchanting was a huge waterfall adjacent to the hot spring pools that cascaded into the bay near the public baths.

It didn’t take us long to immerse ourselves in the water for a good soak. We returned repeatedly both to the bath house and the hot springs over the three days as we waited out what the NOAA weather service called an unusually strong storm, which dumped two inches of rain and spawned 30 knot winds over several days. By the end of the week, we were totally relaxed and mellowed out. Baranof proved to be a wonderful place to be holed up!

A final push through Peril Strait and Sergius Narrows (in the fog!) and we arrived in Sitka for the final days of our 2021 shakedown cruise.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9422-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9422-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9422-768x1024.jpg
Caption: Foghorn working
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Foghorn working]**
*Original filename: IMG_9422-768x1024.jpg*

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9424-scaled.jpg
Filename: IMG_9424-scaled.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9424-scaled.jpg
Caption: Big ship passes us in the fog near Sergius Narrows
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Big ship passes us in the fog near Sergius Narrows]**
*Original filename: IMG_9424-scaled.jpg*]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Glacier Bay</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/06/21/glacier-bay/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glacier Bay" /><published>2021-06-21T19:08:29+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-21T19:08:29+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/06/21/glacier-bay</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/06/21/glacier-bay/"><![CDATA[Casting off from Auke Bay, we partly motored, partly sailed to a place called Swanson’s Harbor about 25 nautical miles from town, tying up for the night to a float maintained there by the great State of Alaska. Several online reviewers complained of bugs at this spot but we didn’t find any. Actually, so far so good as far as bugs go. Even Jocelyn, who is a bug magnet, hasn’t had any trouble.

<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9255-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9255-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9255-1024x768.jpg
Caption: Mother seal and pup near Lamplugh Glacier
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: Mother seal and pup near Lamplugh Glacier]**
*Original filename: IMG_9255-1024x768.jpg*

The next day, June 14th, is Kevin Smith’s birthday. We called him to wish him well. Also on this day, Flag Day, our permit to enter Glacier Bay begins. We had applied online for the permit 60 days earlier, having filled out all the proper forms and pledged to follow all the applicable rules, like watching two fairly lame “orientation videos” telling us to mind our P’s & Q’s while in the Park. Now I think I know why the Alaskans eschew Glacier Bay – too much red tape.

Despite the procedural folderol, June 14th will go down as a red-letter date in the annals of _Windleblo_ history. Remarkably, after so many nautical miles, so many anchorages, so many crossings, so many winter layups, and even a pandemic-induced delay, we were finally going to fully complete the mission. Yes, Sweden to Alaska had been recorded. But it was always Sweden’s Gold Coast to Alaska’s Glacier Bay that was the entire mission. And on this day we were going to accomplish it.

## Dall porpoise escort

As if to herald our achievement, a pod of about 10 Dall porpoises formed on our bow, playfully escorting us the last couple of nautical miles into the bay. I took a video of them and texted it to family and friends using the surprisingly strong cell signal we still enjoyed as we transited the Icy Strait. Once anchored in Bartlett Cove we dinghied ashore for reconnaissance.

In our ignorance, we had expected to find a remote wilderness setting at the Glacier Bay National Park Service headquarters. Maybe a couple of rangers, perhaps a few hardy souls about to head out into the bush. Surprisingly, at the top of the public dock ramp we found not only a full-service guest lodge but a bivy of tourists fresh off the shuttle from Gustavus (pronounced gus-TAVE-us), all busily consuming the free wifi, their heads buried in their phones. The lobby area was full of these folks, seemingly oblivious to the natural world immediately adjacent, apparently preoccupied with their next connection to transfer out. A parking lot seemed full of cars and trucks, something else we did not expect. Turns out, the headquarters is only nine miles down the paved road from Gustavus, easily reached by ferry from Juneau. Who knew?

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9359-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9359-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9359-1024x768.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9359-scaled.jpg)Blackwater pond on forest hike near Bartlett Cove
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9359-scaled.jpg)Blackwater pond on forest hike near Bartlett Cove]**
*Original filename: IMG_9359-1024x768.jpg*

After sussing out the scene, we took a brief hike on a well-maintained trail, ending at 4pm at an outdoor exhibit of one of the world’s few humpback whale skeletons. Ranger James told us the story of “Snow,” the humpback whale interred there, who was clobbered by a cruise ship 20 years ago and killed instantly. According to Ranger James, the NPS made lemonade out of lemons by collecting all of Snow’s bones after she decomposed on the beach, shipping them off to Maine where a specialist treated and preserved them, and finally returning them to Glacier Bay for assembly into the exhibit we now viewed. During the Q&A, as opportunities for whale watching in the bay were reviewed, one couple commented on their recent sighting of mating grizzlies in a nearly cove. Jocelyn and I resolved to keep our eyes peeled for similar sights. 

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9190-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9190-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9190-768x1024.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9190-scaled.jpg)Ranger James telling us the story of “Snow” the humpback whale
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9190-scaled.jpg)Ranger James telling us the story of “Snow” the humpback whale]**
*Original filename: IMG_9190-768x1024.jpg*

One plus to all this civilization…we asked at the front desk if we could have some ice to take with us to the boat. A friendly Park Service employee obliged, sending us away with more than enough ice to chill our vodka tonics. We consumed them in the cockpit as the sun slowly settled in the west, toasting our good fortune and celebrating the accomplishment of having sailed the _Windleblo_ into Glacier Bay.

The rain fell as we weighed anchor the next morning. Now, we would leave civilization behind. From Bartlett Cove, we pointed _Windlebo_ north into the bay. This being a national park, of course there were more rules. We had to stay one nautical mile from shore for the first several miles to keep from disturbing whales and other wildlife. Apparently, there is a greater chance of impacts near the mouth of the bay where the water is shallower and the bay narrows. Once clear of Sitakaday Narrows, the chance for disturbance diminishes and the rules lessen.

A following breeze allowed us to turn off the motor and sail wing-on-wing for much of the day, a real joy given the lack of good sailing conditions around here. We only saw a couple of other boats during the day. Through strict regulation, only 25 recreational vessels are permitted to be in the bay at any one time. One has to leave for another to be allowed entry. A handful of commercial and research vessels are also allowed, so on any given day only about 30 vessels ply the bay’s waters. Due to COVID, we have the good fortune of being here when there are no cruise ships. They don’t start up again until next month, making this a special time to visit.

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9192-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9192-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9192-1024x768.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9192-scaled.jpg)Sailing wing-on-wing on the way to Blue Mouse Cove
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9192-scaled.jpg)Sailing wing-on-wing on the way to Blue Mouse Cove]**
*Original filename: IMG_9192-1024x768.jpg*

So even though our chosen destination was said to be one of the most popular, we hoped to have it to ourselves. Sure enough, as we approached Blue Mouse Cove around mid-afternoon no other boats could be seen. Named after a “well-known theatre in New York” according to one of our cruising guides, Blue Mouse Cove is reputed to offer good wildlife viewing opportunities. We watched a couple of whales feeding nearby as we entered the cove, spouts blowing and flukes flying. Once inside, a harbor seal showed us the way to the anchor spot. In the evening, we watched a black bear forage on the shore nearby. Who knows, maybe we’ll eventually see some humping grizzlies, right?

What we didn’t fully realize, though, was that something much more scintillating than fornicating Yogis awaited us to the north. For after Blue Mouse Cove we entered the real Glacier Bay. The part most clearly sculpted by ice, with tons and tons of it visibly grinding mountains into powder and calving massive towers of itself into the sea.

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9239-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9239-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9239-1024x768.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9239-scaled.jpg)Lamplugh glacier
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9239-scaled.jpg)Lamplugh glacier]**
*Original filename: IMG_9239-1024x768.jpg*

Devoted followers of this blog may recall words uttered by crewman Phil Dear upon experiencing a late-night performance of the world-renowned DJ Tiesto at Ibiza’s Pasha’s night club as part of shore leave from the _Windleblo_ in summer 2012. The morning after, when asked how the evening went, with a starry look in his eyes, he said, “life changing.”

Now on the other side of witnessing Glacier Bay’s glaciers first hand, I am left with a similar characterization of the experience. Like staring into a fire or pondering the Milky Way from high up in the Rockies, watching the tidewater glaciers in action fits the bill for awe inspiring, goosebump inducing, and, yes, life changing qualifiers. One cannot come away from the experience without revisiting primal questions “what is the meaning of life?” “why is there air?” “how big is the universe?” and the like. Texas has nothing on Alaska for biglyness; if there was ever any debate on this point, simply trot out the glaciers and case closed.

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9263-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9263-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9263-768x1024.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9263-scaled.jpg)Breaking through the bergy bits on the dinghy ride to Margerie Glacier
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9263-scaled.jpg)Breaking through the bergy bits on the dinghy ride to Margerie Glacier]**
*Original filename: IMG_9263-768x1024.jpg*

Our glacier witnessing began 12 nautical miles north of Blue Mouse Cove in Reid Inlet where we anchored about a mile across the water from the glacier. All trees had disappeared in those 12 nautical miles and we now found ourselves in an alpine-like environment characterized by rock and low scrub. The steep-sided U-shaped valley contained the glacier, which rose upslope to the southwest. After anchoring in the northwest corner of Reid Inlet, we launched the dinghy to cover the last mile, landing at low tide to walk along the edge of the glacier’s lateral moraine, further progress onto the glacier itself impeded by a fairly wide ice-cold stream of melt water. The glacier had receded several hundred yards from the seawater so even at high tide later the base was not inundated. Consequently, we did not see any calving.

But Reid Glacier was just a warm up for what was to come. The next morning dawned bright, warm, and clear. As at Tracy Arm, it seemed a Colorado bluebird day was again ordered up for our glacier viewing. A further six nautical miles north, we encountered Lamplugh Glacier. Trolling slowly by, the _Windleblo_ provided an excellent platform for viewing the glacier front from about ½ nautical mile away. We were especially impressed by the mountain peaks that served as backdrop for this glacier.

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9308-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9308-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9308-1024x768.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9308-scaled.jpg)Tarr Inlet anchorage
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9308-scaled.jpg)Tarr Inlet anchorage]**
*Original filename: IMG_9308-1024x768.jpg*

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9269-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9269-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9269-1024x768.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9269-scaled.jpg)An extra large berg stranded when the tide went out
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9269-scaled.jpg)An extra large berg stranded when the tide went out]**
*Original filename: IMG_9269-1024x768.jpg*

Seven nautical miles further north, we anchored _Windleblo_ in thick glacial mud and launched the dinghy for a ride one more nautical mile at low tide to a lateral moraine bench adjacent to Margerie Glacier. The bench was littered with ice blocks that had calved from the glacier only to be stranded on the bench as the tide went out. Wandering through the ice blocks, we were mesmerized by the groaning and cracking of the ice as the glacier pushed into the sea. Chunks of ice, some small, some large, plummeted down the glacial front to crash into the sea with a boom. For over two hours, we stared agog at the spectacle, rewarded a few times by a monster calving when a massive tower of ice crashed into the sea creating a huge wave that washed far enough up on the shores of the bench to cause us to seek higher ground.

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9271-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9271-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9271-1024x768.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9271-scaled.jpg)Margerie Glacier at the head of Tarr Inlet
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9271-scaled.jpg)Margerie Glacier at the head of Tarr Inlet]**
*Original filename: IMG_9271-1024x768.jpg*

The tide finally turned and the bench started to become covered again as we retreated to the dinghy and, after looping past the glacier front for a final viewing from a safe distance, returned to the _Windleblo_. All through the evening, we heard further cracking and groaning of the glacier, with the occasional big boom signifying a massive calving, then the rolling of the boat as the wave generated by the falling ice reached us a mile away.

As we motored slowly away in the stillness of the next morning, the surface of the water like glass, we could still hear the glacier talking to us, keeping us mindful us of the awesome power and cosmic energy of Mother Nature and the need to be humble in her presence.

## Sea Lions off South Marble Island

After our up close and personal glacier encounters, our remaining nights in Glacier Bay seemed anti-climactic. Still, relative to garden variety wilderness experiences they were quite impressive. We took in tidal cycles at a North Sandy Cove anchorage, heard the barking and growling of a sea lion colony on South Marble Island, and enjoyed more forest hikes back at Bartlett Cove as our time in the Park came to a close. We even had a close whale encounter as three humpbacks, a mother and two juveniles, were feeding right near our boat as we lay at anchor in Bartlett Cove. Another broached repeatedly for us as we rounded Point Gustavus the next day, bidding us fair winds as we exited the protected whale waters of Glacier Bay National Park and Preserve.

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9370-2-1024x707.jpg
Filename: IMG_9370-2-1024x707.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9370-2-1024x707.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9370-2.jpg)Humpback breaching off Point Gustavus
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9370-2.jpg)Humpback breaching off Point Gustavus]**
*Original filename: IMG_9370-2-1024x707.jpg*]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Casting off from Auke Bay, we partly motored, partly sailed to a place called Swanson’s Harbor about 25 nautical miles from town, tying up for the night to a float maintained there by the great State of Alaska. Several online reviewers complained of bugs at this spot but we didn’t find any. Actually, so far so good as far as bugs go. Even Jocelyn, who is a bug magnet, hasn’t had any trouble.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Juneau</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/06/13/juneau/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Juneau" /><published>2021-06-13T04:51:45+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-13T04:51:45+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/06/13/juneau</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2021/06/13/juneau/"><![CDATA[Two layover days in Juneau. The usual requisites – refuel, reprovision, recharge. But also some great reconnaissance.

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9167-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9167-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9167-1024x768.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9167-scaled.jpg)View from Spaulding Meadows trail
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9167-scaled.jpg)View from Spaulding Meadows trail]**
*Original filename: IMG_9167-1024x768.jpg*

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9150-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9150-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9150-768x1024.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9150-scaled.jpg)On the way to the glacier
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9150-scaled.jpg)On the way to the glacier]**
*Original filename: IMG_9150-768x1024.jpg*

A hike up a wonderful nature trail. Juneau is reputed to have the best hiking trail system in Southeast Alaska. We sampled it.

A bike ride from Auke Bay to downtown Juneau via Mendenhall Glacier. It was only 20 miles but seemed like 40. Probably because we had just sat on a boat for a week.

Wonderful encounters with the natives. Allison welcomed us warmly at the Auke Bay harbor office. The lady bartenders at the local craft brewery were all smiles. Austin and Monica of Sea Globe, a 65-foot Amel ketch, helped us get to and from Safeway and Costco in their pickup truck. (Yes, there’s a Costco in Juneau!) And pretty much everyone we met was very friendly and helpful. Jocelyn even commented that the Alaskans were giving the Canadians a run for their money on being nice.

Oh, and lest I forget, the bald eagles. Here, they’re as common as crows. Some as big as bear cubs. All appear well fed.

Below are a few images of our brief time in Juneau. Next up: Glacier Bay.

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9154-1024x768.jpg
Filename: IMG_9154-1024x768.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9154-1024x768.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9154-scaled.jpg)Mendenhall Glacier
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9154-scaled.jpg)Mendenhall Glacier]**
*Original filename: IMG_9154-1024x768.jpg*

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9159-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9159-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9159-768x1024.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9159-scaled.jpg)The statehouse in downtown Juneau
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9159-scaled.jpg)The statehouse in downtown Juneau]**
*Original filename: IMG_9159-768x1024.jpg*

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9160-768x1024.jpg
Filename: IMG_9160-768x1024.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_9160-768x1024.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9160-scaled.jpg)Allison, a friendly native
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_9160-scaled.jpg)Allison, a friendly native]**
*Original filename: IMG_9160-768x1024.jpg*

[<!-- IMAGE PLACEHOLDER
Original URL: http://windleblo.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_3469-rotated.jpg
Filename: IMG_3469-rotated.jpg
Date path: 2021/06/IMG_3469-rotated.jpg
Caption: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_3469-rotated.jpg)A bald eagle perched on the top of the neighboring boat’s mast in Auke Bay marina
Instructions: Replace this comment with actual image upload
-->

**[IMAGE MISSING: ](/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/IMG_3469-rotated.jpg)A bald eagle perched on the top of the neighboring boat’s mast in Auke Bay marina]**
*Original filename: IMG_3469-rotated.jpg*]]></content><author><name>Jack</name></author><category term="uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Two layover days in Juneau. The usual requisites – refuel, reprovision, recharge. But also some great reconnaissance.]]></summary></entry></feed>